#### Contact

k.k.myers@att.net

www.linkedin.com/in/karen-k-myers (LinkedIn)

#### Top Skills

Healthcare Management Hospitals Nursing

#### Certifications

Acute/Critical Care Nurse - Adult, Pediatric, Neonatal (CCRN)

Johnson & Johnson/Wharton Fellow, Johnson & Johnson/Wharton Fellows Program in Management for Nurse Executives

MHMD University, Jesse H. Jones Graduate School of Business, Rice University Executive Education NEA-BC

#### Honors-Awards

Mary Alice Harris Metcalf Scholarship - Outstanding Doctoral Student

Nursing Celebration Outstanding Nurse

Johnson & Johnson/Wharton Fellow Student Pioneer of Excellence Award

Excellence in Nursing, Bronze Medalist

#### **Publications**

Evaluation of a Standardized Hourly Rounding Process (SHaRP)

# Karen Myers, Ph.D., RN, NEA-BC

CHIEF NURSING OFFICER: Healthcare Executive Houston, Texas Area

#### Summary

Executive leader and performer leading innovative and optimization efforts for healthcare organizations. A trusted and effective collaborator with a broad scope in developing and implementing strategies to create lasting competitive advantage. Effective communicator and negotiator who consistently exercises seasoned judgment and leadership. Substantial experience working with competing demands at multi-site organizations, academic medical centers, and teaching hospitals.

Notable Competencies and Successes: Selected as one of two CNOs to represent nursing on the Memorial Hermann Health System Clinical Operations Leadership Group to prioritize, oversee, monitor, and manage approved clinical operational initiatives throughout the system. Conducted clear and executed comprehensible strategies for large health systems.

Excellence in Nursing Practice: Nurse Executive leading nursing organizations to successful ANCC Magnet® re-designations.

#### Experience

Memorial Hermann Health System 3 years 5 months

Vice President and Chief Nursing Officer (CNO) - Central Region February 2017 - June 2019 (2 years 5 months)

Houston, Texas Area

Provided direction, oversight, and leadership all nursing functions and patient care practices. Oversaw patient care staff of 2,890+ FTEs and an annual operating budget of \$298M of expenses for 1082-bed quaternary care academic medical center hospital serving adult and pediatric patient populations. Oversaw seven direct reports with accountability for patient care

units, Magnet Program, Physical Therapy, Respiratory Therapy, Rehabilitation, Clinical Nutrition, Emergency Department, Ambulatory Clinics, Endoscopy, Heart Failure Program, Stroke Center, Hyperbaric Unit, Nursing, and Patient Education, Staffing Office, Room and Bed Management, Volunteers and PBX Operators with matrix reports for Advanced Practice Providers, Patient Experience and all nursing practice. Reported to the Chief Executive Officer.

Memorial Hermann, Texas Medical Center is a primary teaching hospital for the McGovern Medical School at UTHealth, providing leading-edge care in heart, neuroscience, orthopedics, women's health, general surgery, organ transplantation, and much more. As one of only two certified Level I trauma centers in the greater Houston area, the hospital provides 24/7 emergency and trauma care.

Vice President and Chief Nursing Officer (CNO), Memorial Hermann-Texas Medical Center February 2016 - January 2017 (1 year)

Houston, Texas Area

Provided oversight and leadership for all nursing functions and patient care practices. Directed financial performance, compliance with regulatory standards (national, state, and local), patient satisfaction, patient safety, quality of patient care, productivity, and promotion of Partners-in-Caring. Promoted positive relationships with medical staff and other hospital departments/ personnel. Reported to the Chief Executive Officer.

CHI St. Luke's Health

33 years

Vice President and Chief Nursing Officer (CNO), Baylor St. Luke's Medical Center

January 2006 - November 2015 (9 years 11 months)

Houston, Texas Area

Provided direction and oversight to the President for leadership in the delivery of nursing care, treatment, and services. Oversaw patient care staff of 1750+ FTEs, annual operating budget exceeding \$355M, and six direct reports for patient care units, Palliative Care, Center for Advanced Clinical Practice, Emergency Services, Dialysis, Patient Placement, Nursing Payroll, Nursing Research, and Nursing and Patient Education.

Vice President, Nursing, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital March 1997 - January 2006 (8 years 11 months)

Houston, Texas

## Director, Cardiovascular and Transplant Service, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital

September 1994 - March 1997 (2 years 7 months)

Houston, Texas Area

## Director, Critical Care Nursing Service, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital May 1992 - September 1994 (2 years 5 months)

Houston, Texas Area

## Program Coordinator, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital January 1988 - May 1992 (4 years 5 months)

Houston, Texas Area

## Assistant Nurse Manager/Special Projects, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital

July 1987 - January 1988 (7 months)

Houston, Texas Area

## Interim Nurse Manager, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital May 1987 - June 1987 (2 months)

Houston, Texas Area

#### Assistant Nurse Manager, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital November 1986 - May 1987 (7 months)

Houston, Texas Area

## Unit Teacher, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital 1986 - November 1986 (less than a year)

Houston, Texas Area

## Staff Nurse, Charge Nurse, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital 1982 - 1986 (4 years)

Houston, Texas Area

## The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)

Graduate Assistant Instructor/Consultant 1985 - 1985 (less than a year)

Houston, Texas Area

St. Mary's Hospital Staff Nurse, Medication Nurse 1981 - 1982 (1 year)

Rochester, Minnesota Area

### Education

Texas Woman's University

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Nursing Science · (2019)

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)

Master of Science, Nursing (MSN) · (1983 - 1985)

South Dakota State University

Bachelor of Science - BS, Nursing (BSN) · (1977 - 1981)